Leah: Communication in business
can be broken down into different
types such as formal and informal.
Formal communication is the flow of
information through formal channels
and can be verbal or written.
It is often hierarchical in
nature and controlled by managers.
Lines of communication may go down
and up or even horizontally but are
generally controlled via management
and follow a systematic approach.
Informal communication is based on
personal interactions and relationships.
It can be unstructured and unplanned
and does not follow the formal
channels established by management.
We all communicate in different ways
at different times whether formally
or informally so let’s have a look
at these in a little more detail.
Jack: Verbal communication
involves speaking with others.
It may be face-to face, over the telephone
or via digital media and the internet.
It may also be on a one-to-one
basis or with a group.
Verbal communication can also be formal
or informal in many different ways from
presentations, meetings, interviews,
discussions, to one-on-one conversations,
both personal and for business.
Verbal communication can be
impacted by tone and language and
non-verbal communication elements
and may be backed up by other means
of communication including visual
imagery or written communication.
Leah: Non-verbal communication
includes facial expressions, posture,
eye contact, hand movements and
touch and can be used on its own
or alongside verbal communication.
A listener can communicate their response
non-verbally without saying anything.
Non-verbal communication is often used
formally in meetings and interviews
but is also used informally in social
circumstances and personal relationships.
Jack: Written communication can
traditionally be in the form of a letter,
but often now involves emails, texts,
memos, reports, Tweets, contracts etc.
In the short form they should be clear
and concise, but in the long form
may include more complex information.
However, the speeds and methods of
communication today in the digital
age, can often lead to poorly spelt and
constructed sentences and careless errors.
Written communication can be used
both formally and informally.
Leah: Visual communication is all
around us from posters and ads on
a wall, to images on a TV screen.
We are bombarded by social media
with visual imagery on sites such as
Instagram, Facebook, TikTok and YouTube.
It can also be used in conjunction
with written communication and
verbal communication and often also
involves non-verbal communication.
Visual communication can often be
used to back up verbal communication
within a formal setting such as
work presentations and advertising,
but often it is used informally.